<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Proposals for propagation of the gospel, offered to the Parliament: by Capt. Robert Norvvod.</title>
            <author>Norwood, Robert, Captain.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89760</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1384</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E656_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206655</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865771</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865771</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118022</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89760)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118022)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 101:E656[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Proposals for propagation of the gospel, offered to the Parliament: by Capt. Robert Norvvod.</title>
                  <author>Norwood, Robert, Captain.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "1651. March. 20".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118022:1"/>
            <head>Propoſals for propagation of the GOSPEL, Offered to the PARLIAMENT:</head>
            <byline>By Capt. ROBERT NORVVOOD.</byline>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He occaſion of my preſentment of theſe at this time, is, my being charged of Blaſphemy, (or being a Blaſphemer) at the Committee for propagation of the Goſpel, by M. <hi>Scot</hi> Chair-man thereof.</p>
            <p>Quere, <hi>Whether a Member of the ſame Committee be not guilty of the ſame Blaſphemy (if it be ſo adjudged?)</hi> Then <hi>whether there weer not as much reaſon for me to propoſe, as for him to receive Propoſals?</hi> But if it ſhall not be found Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, then <hi>Whether M.</hi> Scot <hi>ought not in Equity and good Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, give open and publike ſatisfaction, for ſo open and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like an Injury and Scandal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That I do, and ever did acknowledge both Heaven and Hell, and theſe as diſtinct as light and darkneſs, all who know me can witneſs; and my Book dedicated to the Parliament, intituled <hi>Parſon</hi> Simpſon's <hi>Excommunication excommunicated,</hi> (where that Subject, with the other of the Soul is diſcourſed, and to which I could not have anſwer to this day) doth fully teſtifie: A certain local limitted place being only by me deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And to ſay that the Soul of man is of a Divine Eſſence, or of the Eſſence of God, is no more (if rightly underſtood) then to ſay that the Soul is Immortal; or that it was breathed into man from God; or that
<hi>in him we live, and move, and have our Beings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118022:2"/>Hath Capt. <hi>Norwood</hi> been, or is he an Oppreſſor or Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, a Slanderer, Backbiter, or Murderer of his Neighbor? Hath he been, or is he a Swearer, Drunkard, or Adulterer, according to, or after the fleſh? No of a truth, he walks contrary to theſe: Yet reckon I not my ſelf juſtified herewith or hereby, nor judg I any therefore. What then? Why, he hath blaſphemed the abominable Arrogancies and Uſurpations of the Clergy, who would ſit in, upon, and over all mens Conſciences! (Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs M. <hi>Shidrach Simpſon</hi> in my caſe) who have ever done, and ſtill would make the Civil Magiſtrate their whips and rods, their Jaylors, Butchers, and what not?</p>
            <p>The extreme deſparate and vilde deceits of the Lawyers, in the whole courſe or management of the Law in all the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Courts of Juſtice, theſe indeed I have blaſphemed; and this hath been the only and alone cauſe of all my ſufferings, and being charged with Blaſphemy againſt God; which whether I am ſuch, I leave to the judgement of all who know me, have ſeen or read my writings.</p>
            <p>Being thus occaſioned to make this preſentment, and having (as I ſuppoſe) equally with others the liberty of throwing in my mite, and that with you whatever is propoſed ſhall not finde the leſs or more acceptance in reſpect to the Propoſers thereof; (becauſe that were to have the truth in reſpect of perſons contrary to the Scriptures command) Do therefore humbly offer to be conſidered,</p>
            <p>Firſt, What the Goſpel of Chriſt in its very true and real nature, property, and end, in very deed and in truth is? The true and very knowledge whereof, may give light and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in, for, or to its propagation or promulgation.</p>
            <p>The end wherefore I propoſe this, is, leſt whilſt we pretend or intend its propagation, we do not in deed and in truth (ſo much as in us lies) work or bring forth its overthrow and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That which next I ſhould offer to be conſidered is,</p>
            <p>How far any man or men whatſoever, are impowered, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, ordained, and appointed by Chriſt thereunto? or wherein the aptitude and fitneſs of any unto ſuch a work may or doth conſiſt?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118022:2"/>The knowledge of, or true information in the former, will eaſily give us the underſtanding and ſight of this latter.</p>
            <p>That which I take to be the Goſpel, is <hi>Love, Peace, good Will towards men:</hi> Luke 2.14. <hi>Be ye merciful, as your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father is merciful; who cauſes his rain to fall, as upon the good, ſo upon the bad; as upon the juſt, ſo upon the unjuſt.</hi> Matth. 5.45. <hi>Love your Enemies, do good to them that hate you; Bleſs them that curſe you; Pray for them who deſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully uſe you.</hi> Luke 6.27,28. <hi>In this are the children of God. and the children of the Divel manifeſt; Whoſoever doth not Righteouſneſs, is not of God, neither he that loveth not his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: For this is the meſſage we had from the beginning, that we ſhould love one another. Not as</hi> Cain, <hi>who was of that wicked
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſlew his Brother.</hi> 1 John 3.10,11,12. <hi>Hereby have we perceived love, that he laid down his life for us; therefore we alſo ought to lay down our lives for the Brethren:</hi> v. 16. <hi>Hereby we know we are tranſlated from death to life, becauſe we love the Brethren. He that loveth not his Brother, abideth in death; he who hateth his Brother, is a man-ſlayer; and you know no man-ſlayer hath eternal life abiding in him:</hi> v. 14, 15. <hi>Do good to all men, especially to the houſhold of faith. Every one that loveth, is born of God, and knoweth God; he that loveth not, knoweth not God; for God is love. And herein is the love of God manifeſt, that whilſt we were ſinners Chriſt died for us:</hi> 1 John 4.7,8. <hi>A new Commandment</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>give I unto you, that ye love one another, as I have loved you:</hi> John 13.34. And we muſt know, Chriſt and his commands are one and the ſame; his Word and his command is not one thing, and himſelf another: And <hi>he came to ſave ſinners, the chief of ſinners;</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, and himſelf alſo, <hi>I came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance; for the whole need not the Phyſitian, but thoſe that are ſick:</hi> Again he ſaith, <hi>For judgement I am come into this world, that they which ſee not, might ſee;</hi> the following words will be very well worthy the conſideration of moſt men, which is, <hi>and that they who ſee, might be made blinde:</hi> John 9.38. The Phariſees that heard him anſwer, <hi>What? are we blinde alſo?</hi> Chriſt anſwers them, <hi>If ye were blinde, ye ſhould have<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118022:3"/>no ſin; but now you ſay we ſee, therefore your ſin remaineth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God or Chriſt, whoſe end it is (as the Scriptures teſtifie) to magnifie the exceeding greatneſs, the richneſs, the freeneſs and fulneſs; the heights, lengths, bredths, and depths of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; the wonderful glorious dimenſions of it, muſt ſuffer the greateſt ſinners; that ſo he may publiſh himſelf, his Goſpel, the greateſt ſalvation, preach the exceeding greatneſs of his power, and ſo ſave and deliver them from their ſins: as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Sin hath therefore abounded, that the grace of God might ſuperabound:</hi> yet I ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſaid, <hi>Let us not therefore ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This then (if I miſtake not) is the Goſpel of Chriſt, or rather, Chriſt's Goſpel; This is the meſſage and meſſenger God ſent into the world; for the meſſage and meſſenger muſt be one and the ſame thing; This is that Son of Righteouſneſs, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that righteous Son God ſent into the world: Chriſt he preaches what himſelf and his Father indeed and in truth are; commands and promiſes what we ſhould and muſt be and do, if we receive his meſſage, his promiſe, and obey his command. We ſee Chriſt did not ſpeak and preach only, but he did, and appeared really in all things to be the ſame which he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; prays when they were putting him to death, <hi>Father, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them, they know not what they do:</hi> (ſo doth <hi>Stephen</hi> alſo) and heals his ear who came to apprehend him, which <hi>Peter</hi> had cut off; gives his life for his enemies: And this is that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Love, not in dead word, but in deed and in truth, in the life and power of it; which love</hi> (as the Scriptures teſtifie) <hi>is God:</hi> and <hi>which</hi> (as
<hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) <hi>thinketh none ill, but it beareth all things, ſuffers all things, endures all things: Love it covereth all ſins;</hi> Prov. 10.12. <hi>Love, it worketh none ill to his Neighbour;</hi> Rom. 13.10. And this is that promiſed in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.2,3,4. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in the laſt days, that the mountain of the Lord's houſe ſhall be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the top of the mountains, and ſhall be exalted above the hills; and all Nations ſhall flow unto it. And many people ſhall go and ſay, Come ye, and let us go up to the mountain of the Lord, to the houſe of the God of</hi> Jacob; <hi>and he will teach us of his ways, and we will walk in his paths<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for out of<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118022:3"/>Zion ſhall go forth a Law, and the word of the Lord from Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. And he ſhall judge among the Nations, and rebuke many people: and they ſhall beat their ſwords into plow-ſhares, and their ſpears into pruning hooks: Nation ſhall not lift up ſword againſt Nation, neither ſhall they learn war any more.</hi> and in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.6,7,8,9. <hi>The Wolf alſo ſhall dwell with the Lamb, and the Leopard ſhall ly down with the Kid; and the Calf, and the young Lyon, and the Fatling together, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle childe ſhall lead them. And the Cow and the Bear ſhall feed, their young ones ſhall ly down together; and the Lyon ſhall eat ſtraw like the Ox: And the ſucking Childe ſhall play on the hole of the Aſpe, and the weaned Childe ſhall put his hand on the Cockatrise den. They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy mountain: for the earth ſhall be full of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the Sea.</hi> And in <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.31,32,33,34. <hi>Behold, the days come, ſaith the Lord, that I will make a new Covenant with the houſe of Iſrael, and with the houſe of Judah: Not according to the Covenant that I made with their Fathers in the day that I took them by the hand, to bring them out of the land of Egypt, which my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant they brake, although I was an husband unto them, ſaith the Lord. But this ſhall be the Covenant which I will make with the houſe of Iſrael; After thoſe days, ſaith the Lord, I will put my Law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts, and will be their God, and they ſhall be my people. And they ſhall teach no more every man his Neighbour, and every man his brother, ſaying, Know the Lord: for they ſhall all know me, from the leaſt of them unto the greateſt of them, ſaith the Lord; for I will forgive their iniquity, and I will remember their ſin no more.</hi> There you have Chriſt promiſed as a living life, dwelling and abiding in the ſoul, or law written in the heart, ſo that we ſhall not at all hang upon the lips of men, or have any need or uſe of their teachings. Whether this then be not in deed and in truth the very reall and true Goſpe of Chriſt, or Chriſt's Goſpel; God's Spell, or good Spell; is offered and left (together with the ſeveral Scriptures quoted, with many others coherent thereunto, which for brevity ſake I omit) to your due inſpection, and ſerious conſideration. And if this be <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118022:4"/>indeed and in truth Chriſt's Goſpel, God's Spel, or good Spell, as it's ſuppoſed it will not by any be denied: The next thing to be conſidered, is,</p>
            <p>How far any man or men whatſoever are impowered, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, ordained, appointed, fitted, furniſhed, enabled, or anointed by Chriſt hereunto; all theſe names ſignifying indeed but one and the ſame thing; for he who is not fitted, furniſhed, enabled or anointed thereunto, is not impowered, conſtituted, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, or appointed by God or Chriſt thereunto; the ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men in this point will not do except they could give the thing alſo; the inward anointing as well as the outward.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Apoſtles, although they had the promiſe, yet they were not to ſtir, they were not to go forth to preach the Goſpel, until themſelves had received the Goſpel, the promiſe of the Father; until they were indued with power from on high; <hi>Luke</hi> 24.49. <hi>And behold I do ſend the promiſe of my Father upon you; but tarry ye in the City of Jeruſalem until ye be indued with power from on high:</hi> Acts 1.8.
<hi>Ye ſhall receive the holy Ghoſt:</hi> Here's a further confirmation of the promiſe; but yet they ſtir not, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1.4. there it is ſaid, <hi>They were all filled with the holy Ghoſt:</hi> Now have they the performance of the promiſe; now and not before were they Commiſſioned, ordained, impowered, or appointed; becauſe now, and not before really and actually anoynted, and then indeed were they anointed or baptiſed, in, with, or unto the preaching of Chriſt's Goſpel unto others; and then they indeed do go forth preaching, baptiſing healing all manner of diſeaſes caſting out divels, and the like; freely they had received, and freely they were to give; and ſo indeed they did: as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to the Cripple whom he healed; <hi>Silver and Gold have I none, but ſuch as I have, that give I unto you: Riſe up and walk: And he lift him up by the hand, healed him, and he walked.</hi> Thereby manifeſting and declaring, what the Goſpel, what the Anointing, what the Miſſage or Meſſage was they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and accordingly did give forth the ſame; as is declared.</p>
            <p>And indeed nothing can give that which it hath not, or more then it hath; neither can any thing act beyond the <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118022:4"/>power or ability it hath received: If the power be of men, the anointing of and by men, why accordingly is and muſt needs be in its ſpeakings and goings forth, its actings and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; for no ſtream can run higher, or above its head or ſpring: <hi>That which is born of the fleſh: is fleſh; that which is born of the Spirit, is Spirit:</hi> If it be from men, its living is and muſt needs be in and upon men, and its returns unto men; If of and from God, its living is and will be only in and upon God, and its returns only unto or into God. Wherefore it is as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 5.44. <hi>How can ye believe who receive Honour one from another, and ſeek not the honour that cometh from God alone:</hi> Whence I argue, He that hath not himſelf received the Goſpel in deed and in truth, He that hath not received the meſſage (as is before declared) that hath not received it in life and power, that is not thus anointed of God, cannot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in deed and in truth preach the Goſpel unto another: He who preaches the Goſpel, muſt be Goſpelized, Evangelized, muſt be in very deed and truth the very thing he ſpeaks and preaches.</p>
            <p>The Goſpel is not, the kingdom of Chriſt is not letter, or dead word onely, but it is life and power; it is not a dead Chriſt, but a living Chriſt, or Chriſt indeed and in truth dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or living lively and powerfully in fleſh, manifeſting, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or ſpeaking forth it ſelf by or through fleſh, and that not in or by dead word or letter only, but in power and life, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by real, ſenſible, and ſutable acts, as is before quoted; according as is alſo in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2,3. <hi>Ye are our Epiſtle, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in our hearts, which is underſtood and read of all men; in that ye are manifeſt to be the Epiſtle of Chriſt, miniſtred by us; and written (not with Inke, but) with the Spirit of the living God; not in Tables of ſtone, but in the fleſhly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the heart.</hi> Thus as the Goſpel was received in power, ſo was it again preached or given forth in power; What <hi>Paul</hi> had received, that he alſo communicated: which what it was, you there ſee.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I leave it to be duly weighed and conſidered, whether it be not neceſſary that he who goes forth to preach the Goſpel of God or Chriſt, or Chriſt's Goſpel, or God's <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118022:5"/>Gods Spell, or good Spell, be not thus ordained; appointed, impowered or anointed of God, as is before expreſſed; And that he do indeed and in truth receive his power or anoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not from below; not from men, but from God, or from above.</p>
            <p>And then, Whether any are-thus ordained, appointed or anoynted? and who, and where thoſe are?</p>
            <p>And then, if there be any ſuch,</p>
            <p>Whether they do not highly diſhonour their Lord and Maſter, in ſeeking power from below, or from men; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; yea, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the very nature of the thing, or power it ſelf they pretend to?</p>
            <p>It was ſaid by ſome of the Clergy at the Committee, To what end or purpoſe was it for them to propoſe any thing to the Parliament, were it not in their power, or the power of the Magiſtrate to make Lawes in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and to puniſh the Breakers of thoſe Lawes ſo made?</p>
            <p>As much as if they had ſaid, To what end is it for us to preach and proclaim the Goſpel of God or Chriſt, although ordained, impowered, conſtituted, appointed, and anoynted thereunto by God or Chriſt, except you (the Civil Magiſtrate) do not, or will not onely tolerate and allow us, but incourage and protect us alſo therein; nay except you alſo follow after us with your ſwords to cut all their throats, who believe not as we believe; who do not hear or receive the things we ſay and ſpeak although we can indeed and in truth give no better reaſon, nor ſhew any better Commiſſion then our bare ſay ſo? Which whether it be not quite contrary to a Goſpel Spirit, I leave to be conſidered; yea contrary to Chriſt's and the Apoſtles both precepts and practiſes; <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.38. to the end,
<hi>Ye have heard that it hath been ſaid, An eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth. But I ſay unto you, That ye reſiſt not evil: but whoſoever ſhall ſmite thee on thy right cheek, turne to him the other alſo. And if any man will ſue thee at the law, and take away thy coat, let him have thy cloak alſo. And whoſoever ſhall compel thee to go a mile, go with him twain. Give to<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118022:5"/>him that asketh thee: and from him that would borrow of thee, turn thou not away. Ye have heard that it hath been ſaid, Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour and hate thine enemy: but I ſay unto you, Love your enemies, bleſs them that curſe you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight ſully uſe you, and hate you: That ye may be the children of your Father which is in heaven: for he maketh his ſun to riſe on the evil, and on the good, and ſendeth his rain on the juſt, and unjuſt. For if ye love them which love you, what reward have ye? do not even the publicans the ſame? And if ye ſalute your brethren onely what do ye more then others? do not even the publicans ſo? Be ye therefore perfect, even as your Father which is in heaven is perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, indeed and in truth, is The Goſpel of Chriſt; or, this is Chriſt's Goſpel indeed and in truth: and it lies not in a few outſide preachings, prayings, baptizings, humiliations, thankſgivings, and the like; not in any or all the outward viſible Forms of admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration whatſoever, that ever were, are, or ſhall be; but this written in the heart, this ſpirit living and dwelling in us in life and power; ſpeaking and preaching, acting and working it ſelf forth by real, viſible, and ſenſible demonſtrations; which the beſt of us all I fear, notwithſtanding our ſo high pretenſions, are ſo far from being anointed with, ſo as to preach to others, that we cannot, nor are we able to bear almoſt the very hearſay of it from others.</p>
            <p>Now this living life of God in our ſpirits, or this law of God written in our hearts by the Spirit of God, is indeed and in truth the Goſpel: upon whomſoever it falls, it will make all his earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and fleſhlineſs to tremble and fall; and he who looks upon it, will preſently lower all his ſtately plumes: there is Chriſt's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept: for preſident, look into <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.54,55,56. when being refuſed to be entertained and received by the Samaritans, <hi>John</hi> and <hi>James</hi> would that they might, as <hi>Elias</hi> did, command fire from heaven to have conſumed them:
<hi>but Jeſus rebuked them, ſaying. Ye know not of what ſpirit ye are: for the Son of man is not come to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi> So when <hi>Peter</hi> attempted his reſcue from thoſe who came to apprehend him, he reproves him, ſaying, <hi>He that kills with the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword:</hi> and further ſaith, he could pray unto the Father, <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118022:6"/>and he would ſend him more then twelve legions of angels but his kingdom is not of this world; as he ſays
<hi>Joh.</hi> 13.36. <hi>My Kingdom is not</hi> &amp;c. <hi>if my kingdom were of this world my ſervants would ſurely fight for me: but now my kingdom is not from hence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore then ſince Chriſts kingdom is not of this world, as indeed and in truth it is not, but diametrically oppoſite and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to it; therefore is it not to be propagated ſupported maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or defended, with or by any the weapons of this world: And that whenas he himſelf would not, in his own perſon, or by any other, defend himſelf, or be defended by any outward force, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or power whatſoever; I offer it to conſideration, whether any other man or men whatſoever, may or ought to do it. And if his Kingdom be ſpiritual (as it's ſaid it is) what then ſhould carnal weapons do in it or about it? And then, whether thoſe who give counſel to States and Commonwealths herein, give not counſel evidently and eminently deſtructive to them? For no one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, precept, or preſident is there given for it by Chriſt, or any of his Apoſtles, who brought, preached, and publiſhed the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; but the quite contrary, as hath been ſhewed.</p>
            <p>I would next offer to conſideration, what ſurer or better preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the preſent Clergie have, may, or can have, to the Chair of
<hi>Peter,</hi> to the power given from on high, to the appointing or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointing of the Father, then hath the Romiſh, Epiſcopal, or other Clergie, that what they propoſe, preach, or publiſh, ſhould be more obliging or binding then others?</p>
            <p>And then, whether they can pretend any more or further to the ſpirit of infallibility, for the opening thoſe myſteries of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the myſteries of Chriſt; or to open, unfold, and truly to declare Chriſt, who is the Myſtery of myſteries: <hi>Great is the myſtery of godlineſs, Chriſt manifeſt in fleſh.</hi> Perhaps they think it eaſie, (let them take heed, that, leſt ſeeing, they be made blinde;) but Chriſt himſelf ſaith, in <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.27. <hi>No man knoweth the Son, but the Father.</hi> Or whether they be able to unriddle the riddles, open the parables declared by Chriſt: for it's written, <hi>Without a parable ſpake he not:</hi> Or to unſeal the book ſpoken of by <hi>John</hi> in the
<hi>Revelations.</hi> And if any man underſtand not theſe myſteries as they do, unfold or open theſe riddles or parables according to their ſence, meaning, or interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118022:6"/>he muſt preſently, without all doubt or peradventure, be an Heretick or Blaſphemer.</p>
            <p>And then, from the conſideration of what Chriſt and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, as it is held forth unto us in the Scriptures quoted, and many other coherent thereunto, whether the conſtituting or appointing any other laws by any, in reference to the promulgation and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation thereof, other then are by himſelf expreſly commanded and appointed, be not derogatory unto, if not a denying of Chriſt himſelf, whom we lay and affirm to be the onely and alone King, Prieſt, and Prophet, in and unto his Church and people.</p>
            <p>And then, whether it be not (upon the fore-going grounds) indeed and in truth the ſpirit of Antichriſt. as in their predeceſſors, ſo now riſen up again in theſe their ſucceſſors, labouring and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring, by all the force and power they can, and by all the ſubtil devices they are able, to engage, ſtir up, and incite, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, powers for the ſupport, defence, and maintenance of their own kingdom, under colour and pretence of defending the Kingdom of Chriſt, which he diſclaims (as is before proved;) and under the notion of ſuppreſſing Blaſphemy and Hereſie, that ſpirit doth not, in very deed and in truth, aim at, labour and endeavour the ſuppreſſing of the very Truth it ſelf; as it hath conſtantly been ſeen to this day (though perhaps, and I do verily believe, many of them ſee or know it not.) Verily, Truth is ſeldom or never heard in out-cries againſt others; it's ſeldom whiſpering againſt, or ſecretly backbiting of any: Truth is ſtrong, and therefore not eaſily oftended: it willingly hurts no man, becauſe it knows no man can hurt it. Verily, that's not worth owning, that will not ſtand alone by it ſelf: Wherefore I ſay, Let them alone, to ſtand or fall to their own maſter: and if Chriſt be their Maſter, what need they fear?</p>
            <p>I ſhould therefore offer: As you have already broken the Head of that Abaddoniſm in this Nation, that ſame perſecuring ſpirit, that ſame ſpirit of diviſion and dividings: ſo, that you would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo cut off its Tayl. Not that I would have them, or any other, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured, troubled, perſecuted, or moleſted: no; for that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Goſpel, as is already declared: it were contrary to that rule alſo which ſaith, <hi>Love thy neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> and, <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118022:7"/>
               <hi>Do to all men as thou wouldſt they ſhould do to thee;</hi> nay, as thou wouldſt God ſhould do to thee; and, Do not that unto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, that thou wouldſt not another man ſhould do to thee. And indeed, herein is the fulfilling of the whole Law, and <hi>on this</hi> (as Chriſt ſaith) <hi>hangeth</hi> or dependeth <hi>all the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets:</hi> this being, indeed and in truth, all in all: this, and this onely, being the onely and alone neceſſary and fundamental thing, ſo far as I can, or ever could underſtand: It, and it onely, ſerving and enduring in and unto all ſorts of men whatſoever. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is, that <hi>Paul,</hi> (in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
12. the four laſt verſes; and the eight firſt verſes of the thirteenth Chapter) after he had reckoned up all the moſt glorious gifts of the Spirit, as Apoſtles, Prophets, Teachers, workers of Miracles, Gifts, Healings, Helps, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, diverſities of Tongues; but, ſaith he, <hi>Study earneſtly the beſt gifts:</hi> and <hi>yet</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhew I unto you a more excellent way:</hi> intimating, there was ſomething more deſirable, more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then all or any of theſe; as in the thirteenth Chapter it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears. <hi>And God hath ſet ſome in the church, firſt apoſtles, ſecondarily prophets, thirdly teachers, after that miracles, then gifts of healings, helps in governments, diverſities of tongues. Are all apoſtles? are all prophets? are all teachers? are all workers of miracles? have all the gifts of healing? do all ſpeak with tongues? do all interpret? But covet earneſtly the beſt gifts: and yet ſhew I unto you a more excellent way. Though I ſpeak with the tongue of men and angels, and have not charity, I am become as ſounding braſs, or a tinkling cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal. And though I have the gift of prophecie, and underſtand all myſteries, and all knowledge; and though I have all faith, ſo that I could remove mountains, and have no charity, I am nothing. And though I beſtow all my goods to feed the poor, and though I give my body to be burned, and have not cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, it profiteth me nothing. Charity ſuffereth long, and is kinde: charity envieth not: charity vannteth not it ſelf, is not puffed up; doth not behave it ſelf unſeemly, ſeeketh not her own, is not eaſily provoked, thinketh no evil, rejoyceth not in iniquity, but rejoyceth in the truth: beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things.<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118022:7"/>Charity never faileth: but whether there be propheſies, they ſhall fail; whether there be tongues, they ſhall ceaſe; whether there be knowledge, it ſhall vaniſh away,</hi> So that here you ſee, Love or Charity is preferred before and above all other things: and the reaſon of it (as you ſee alſo) is becauſe it, and it onely, is everlaſting: for it is God, or Chriſt, as the Scriptures teſtifie; God or Chriſt made viſible, manifeſt, born or brought forth in fleſh: Apoſtles, Prophets, Teachers, may, nay muſt ceaſe; nay, all things but it: then it, and it onely, is and can be Fundamental. The Temple, with all the rites, laws, and adminiſtrations thereof, are ceaſed, and done away: the Brazen ſerpent, one eſpecial type and figure of Chriſt after the fleſh, it alſo, when idolized, is ſtamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to powder, and done away: the Prieſthood muſt be changed from
<hi>Levi</hi> to <hi>Judah,</hi> as it was in Chriſt: Chriſt himſelf alſo, as he was after the fleſh, muſt be crucified; that <hi>veil</hi> rent, and done away: as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, he will know no man after the fleſh; no, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet henceforth would he know him ſo no more: ſo alſo, all thoſe things that had their dependence thereupon, or related thereunto; as it is in the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews: Leaving</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the doctrine of the beginning of Chriſt, let us go forward unto perfection, not laying again the foundation of repentance from dead works and of the doctrine of Baptiſms, and laying on of hands, and of the reſurrection from the dead, and of the eternal judgement;</hi> as if theſe things would not make perfect: if they could, we are not to leave them. The ſame thing appears by that which was before cited: <hi>Ye ſhall no more need teach one another, ſaying, Know the Lord: for all ſhall know me, from the greateſt to the leaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſo far from having any who in any kinde whatſoever differ or diſſent in opinion from me, therefore to be perſecuted, moleſted, or troubled, that I would have him in all things have the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect from the State equal with my ſelf: Provided he keep cloſe, faſt, and firm to that rule of doing to everyman as he would every man ſhould do to him; and ſo, of not doing that to any man, which he would not any ſhould do to him. And in this, and this only (to my underſtanding) is the care, diligence, and induſtry of the Magiſtrate to be exerciſed; and for the breach hereof, is the ſword onely to be<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118022:8"/>drawn. Where, or in whom this Goſpel is not indeed and in truth preached; where, or in whoſe heart this Law is not written, or where any man or men whatſoever are deſtitute or fall ſhort in this, or tranſgreſs herein, then, and therein onely (if at any time, according to the Goſpel) is the Magiſtrate to ſtep in, and by his power to make up ſuch neglects or defects: therefore it's ſaid, <hi>The law was not made for arighteous man, but for the diſobedient and ſinner:</hi> and he who breaks that royal, and onely royal law, Love ſhall unavoidably ſuffer in or with the breach thereof.</p>
            <p>That I would then humbly, ſeriouſly and faithfully adviſe and move you unto, is, That you would try every ſpirit, whence it comes, and whither it tends: ſee whether it be of God and Chriſt, or no: try it by what is here laid down; try it by the Goſpel which you would propagate. Can any but a truely-Goſpel-ſpirit, in truth propagate the Goſpel, or propagate the Goſpel in truth? Take heed leſt this ſpirit, if you receive it, if you hearken unto and embrace it and its counſels, prove not as dangerous and fatal as it hath to thoſe who have gone before: and whether by theſe means, and upon theſe occaſions, many of the truely real, ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly godly, upright hearted people of this Nation, have not been, and are very much eſtranged from you? And think you that you will be able to ſpare any ſuch? Are not hereby diviſions and animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties fomented, cheriſhed, nouriſhed, and increaſed, betwixt us, and amongſt us? And will the preſent ſtate of things well bear this? Nay, hath not this Commonwealth often loſt, and been bereaved, by theſe means and occaſions, of its beſt and moſt faithful mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers?</p>
            <p>You have now ſeen (according to my underſtanding) what the very Goſpel indeed and in truth is; and what ſpirit it is that muſt indeed and in truth propagate this Goſpel; even a Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirit, an Evangelized or Evangelical ſpirit: and, indeed and in truth, none elſe can, as hath likewiſe been ſhewed and proved. You may likewiſe now in part determine, where, or whether there be (at preſent, or as yet) in very deed and truth, any ſuch ſpirit, or no; whatever the thoughts and high pretenſions of ſome men are. Then, it's not (I humbly conceive) unworthy conſideration, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Chriſt, that <hi>man-childe,</hi> according as S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks,<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118022:8"/>was not, before that great deſection in the Apoſtles times, taken up again into heaven, there to remain until the appointed time; for whom, or for whoſe coming again in greater power and glory then before, all who have the firſt fruits of the ſpirit, in great, ful, and aſſured hopes and expectations, do and muſt wait, bearing their witneſs in ſackcloth to him, and to that day of his appearing, with watchfulneſs: when, by whom, or at what time, the book ſhall be unſealed, all the myſteries of Chriſt and his Kingdom made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, opened, or revealed. Wherefore being, if I miſtake not, in that juncture of time, where it is ſaid, that it was <hi>neither day nor night, but in the evening it ſhould be light,</hi> I conceive that great care ſhould be had of ſtigmatizing any with blaſphemy and hereſie, but rather leave it to the Great Day to declare them.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, for propagation of the Goſpel (if it may be by us done) I ſhould humbly offer, that there be a removal, ſo far and ſo much as may be, of all and every thing, which, in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and property, is evidently and eminently, viſibly and certainly deſtructive or contrary thereunto.</p>
            <p>As firſt, that inquiſition be made for, and repeal had, of all ſuch Statutes, Orders, Ordinances, and Acts of Parliament, any ways tending that way: for it's better (if I may ſo ſpeak) that many Errours and Hereticks eſcape unpuniſhed by the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate (had he indeed a rightful power thereunto) then that one true witneſs of Chriſt ſhould ſuffer; that many tares ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the field, and grow together with the wheat until the time of harveſt, (as Chriſt himſelf ſaith) when it's eaſie to diſtinguiſh, then by plucking them up before, endanger the wheat alſo. The earth hath done, may do, nay, muſt help the woman, though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny falſe Prophets may, nay ſhall ariſe, inſomuch that they ſhould deceive the very elect, if it were poſſible; but it's not poſſible: and it's neceſſary (as the Scripture ſpeaks) that ſuch ſhould be; that they which are approved may be made manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that all compulſive and forcible maintenance for ſuch who call themſelves the Miniſters of the Goſpel, be alſo removed and done away, becauſe it's contrary to the rules of the Goſpel, and to the command of Chriſt, which ſaith, Take onely the things that are ſet before you by thoſe who receive you: but they were<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118022:9"/>not to carry away any thing with them; for they were not to have ſo much as a ſcrip to put it in: and were onely to caſt off the duſt of their feet againſt them that received them not.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that there may be no outward compulſions or enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of any, to receive their, or any other mens doctrines or principles; neither that any mulcts, fines, baniſhments, or any other corporal puniſhment, be inflicted upon thoſe that receive them not, or who write, preach, or ſpeak againſt any others; ſo that no affronts, injury, or violence, be done by the one unto the other: becauſe theſe things alſo, as is before declared, are humbly conceived to be diametrically oppoſite and contrary to Chriſt and his Goſpel. I ſhall, for further confirmation, offer to your conſideration that in <hi>Luke</hi> 12. where Chriſt is likened unto a man that had taken a journey into a far country, and bids them therefore have their loyns always girt about, and their lamps burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, waiting for their maſters coming; pronounceth him bleſſed that thus continues watching, becauſe he knows not what hour he will come in: he bleſſeth that ſervant that giveth forth the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſeaſon; but he who ſhall begin to ſmite his fellow-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, even that ſervant he will cut off. Wherefore according to the Law, he who injures not his brother in any kinde, let him not in any kinde be injured by his brother: and herein may the Civil Magiſtrate interpoſe, (as I conceive) if his help and aſſiſtance be required: but if the one will forgive, pardon, and paſs by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury and offence of the other, it's better.</p>
            <p>I ſhould laſtly offer, that thoſe who are growing up into, or unto the ſpirit of the Goſpel, or unto a Goſpel-ſpirit, be not, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to theſe rules, rejected, injured, or moleſted; but rather (I ſay rather) cheriſhed.</p>
            <p>There are other things might be propoſed; being ſuppoſed to be done by others, I omit them, and leave you unto this rule, <hi>That what you would any other man ſhould do to you, that do you, or let be done unto them:</hi> and ſo, <hi>Whatever you would not that any other man or men ſhould do unto you that do not you do nor let be done unto them:</hi> for, what meaſure you mete unto others, muſt and ſhall be meaſured unto you again; becauſe God is juſt.<pb facs="tcp:118022:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Let us be in or under what time or diſpenſation ſoever; be it mixt, as neither dark nor light, neither day nor night, neither perfectly under the diſpenſation or adminiſtration of the Law, nor yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the diſpenſation or adminiſtration of the Goſpel; but as it were partly the one, and partly the other; This rule will be light and ſtrength unto you in this, yea and in all otherthings, ſtates, and conditions whatſoever, (as is before noted) even
<hi>as a light ſhining in a dark place,</hi> if well looked upon, duely weighed and conſidered.</p>
            <p>As ſuppoſe the queſtion ſhould be, Whether the Jews ſhould be tolerated amongſt us, or no This Law and Goſpel ſaith Yes; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we would, if under their power, that they ſhould tolerate us. And herein I meddle not with States-men, nor that which is called <hi>Reaſon of State</hi> but leave that and them to ſtand and fall to their and its own maſter (I ſpeak <hi>ad rem</hi>;) I ſpeak onely to what is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and ſo much cried up, and called out for; which, now it is decalred but in the letter onely, how few receive it lo but when it is or ſhall be decalred, manifeſted, or preached, as it is indeed and in truth in the power of it, few, I fear, will be found to embrace, own, ſhew forth, and practiſe the ſame in its life and power. Though I could ſay ſomething alſo as to that which is called <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of State,</hi> or State-Reaſon, or rather, State-Police: but that's not my buſineſs here, nor at this time.</p>
            <p>More might be ſaid for their reception and toleration<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As firſt, We cannot be perfect without them: ſecondly, Our ſalvation came by their ſtumbling or falling; and that as their diminiſhing was the riches of the Gentiles, how much more ſhall their abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance be and if the caſting off of them (onely for a time) be the reconciling of the world, what ſhall their receiving be, but life from the dead I (as <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle of the Gentiles argues, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.) So that we are but in a condition of death, or dead condition (at leaſt comparatively) until they be received in again. And again, he ſaith, <hi>Boaſt not thy ſelf againſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>: be not high-minded but fear; leſt as God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ared not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural branches, ſo he do not ſpare thee, but that thou be broken off alſo as they were.</hi> The whole Chapter is worthy a moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, conſideration. We daily pray for them; let it therefore<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118022:10"/>really and truly appear that we be what we ſeem (or would ſeem) to be.</p>
            <p>I leave it, in the laſt place, ſeriouſly to be conſidered, Whether in all Ages, Kingdoms, and States, the Clergie have not been the chief, if not the onely occſioners, if not the ſomenters, hatchers, plotters and contrivers of all the conſiderable or eminent treaſons, treacheries, conſpiracies wars, and bloodſhed, thorowout all or moſt part of
<hi>Europe;</hi> and that under the name or notion of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the Kingdom and Goſpel of Chriſt. All (whether they have been Princes Kingdoms States, or private perſons) who have at any time, in any age, diſſented from, diſowned or diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed their preachings or practices, their doctrines or principles, have by them been conſtantly purſued with Excommunications, Execrations, Sword, Fire, and Fagot; and yet they are all for the Goſpel. You ſhall finde that this ſpirit hath riſen up in and with every degree, ſort, or ſect of them, as all our Hiſtories do unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly declare (I ſpeak onely as to the generality; there are good and godly, peaceable and quiet-minded men amongſt them, but it is <hi>rara avis in terra</hi>:) as if indeed it were intailed to them, or they intailed to it. This is the anointing they have received, an anointing from belowe, from the bottomleſs pit; not from heaven or from above: it's not a Goſpel-anointing; <hi>ecce ſignum,</hi> the tree is known by its fruits: you ſhall finde them one day cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, <hi>Hereſie, hereſie, blaſphemy, blaſphemy, fire, fagot,</hi> what not? and the next day, <hi>Hoſanna to the Higheſt:</hi> that's hereſie and blaſphemy to day, nay this hour, which the next day or hours is ſound Orthodoxal truth. Have not our eyes oſt ſeen, and our ears oft heard this thing? Is it not now at preſent ſeen daily amongſt us? I never yet have ſeen, read, or heard, that the Clergie were true to the intereſt of any Kingdom, State, or Commonwealth, any longer then ſuch Kingdom, State or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth was true to their private and particular intereſts and accommodations.</p>
            <p>The former Clergie would be ſtill crying up and praying for the Houſe and Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> although they pretended ſomewhat from Chriſt alſo, who was of <hi>Judah:</hi> but had they plainly or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly held from <hi>Judah,</hi> from Chriſt, they had upon all accounts
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118022:10"/>loſt all manner of claim to their Tythes or Tenths; therefore they will hold and derive from <hi>Levi,</hi> which indeed was the beſt and ſafeſt claim. But whence theſe men hold, claim or derive, I know not, nor, I think themſelves neither: ſurely they finde their foundation to be weak and rotten, they take ſo much care, uſe ſo much diligence and induſtry for its ſupport. Why, fear not, if you and your doctrines have their foundation in and upon Chriſt, they ſhall, they muſt ſtand, let the windes blowe, the floods beat. Why, man, Chriſt is a Rock.</p>
            <p>Oh, but they blaſpheme our God, and that we cannot bear with; ſuch the Magiſtrate muſt puniſh.</p>
            <p>Why <hi>James,</hi> why <hi>John,</hi> ye know not what ſpirit ye are on: let God alone to avenge his own quarrel; <hi>Vengeance is mine, ſaith the Lord and I will repay it.</hi> Think you, is not your God ſtrong enough, or wiſe enough? But hear what <hi>David</hi> ſaith; <hi>Lord my goodneſs</hi> (or, my righteouſneſs) <hi>extends not unto thee, but unto the Saints on earth:</hi> And if our righteouſneſs (which is our ſtrength) reach not him, as in truth it neither doth, nor can do; Will our unrighteouſneſs or ſins (think you) which is our weakneſs, reach or exten'd to him? Be not ſo ignorant: God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be moved more or leſs, either with this or that: for he is wholly or altogether unchangable. But let me tell you, You blaſpheme him, in ſetting him below himſelf, as he is in his own pure nature and eſſence, ever and always the ſame, from eternity to eternity; an unchangeable <hi>IS.</hi> You blaſpheme him, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming him to the world to be a cruel, mercileſs, and unnatural Father. Will the father deſtroy the ſon of his loyns? and will God do ſuch a thing, think you? Doth not Chriſt tell you, if your earthly parents know how to give good gifts unto their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, much more doth your heavenly Father? Will God, think you, puniſh a man that's born blinde becauſe he cannot ſee, neither is it at all in his power to get himſelf eyes? But you would have men puniſhed for denying Chriſt, although none can know or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him, without the power, help, and aſſiſtance of him who is altogether above and beyond his reach and power: for, as hath been before cited, <hi>None can know the Son, but the Father:</hi> And again, <hi>None can call Jeſus the Chriſt, but by the Spirit.<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118022:11"/>No man cometh unto me, except the Father draw him.</hi> And yet you ſay. This is the minde, will, or command of God. Is not this extreme highly to blaſpheme, or blaſt the ſame, do to ſpeak very evilly of God, and to cauſe others to do ſo alſo? Conſider who ſo much as your ſelves do in very deed and in truth blaſpheme the true and very God, and his Chriſt and the true and very Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of the true and very Chriſt. Let all the world ſee, and hear, and judge. Whatever is unreaſonable, is none of Gods ſpelling or telling; is not the Goſpel of Chriſt, or is none of Chriſts Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. Nature, or rather, Reaſon or Lightim nature; ſaith to all men, in all things, <hi>Do to all men as you would be done unto:</hi> but grace, or Gods ſpell or Good ſpell the reaſon or light therein (for there is Reaſon in Grace and Goſpel, as well as in Nature, as I could ſhew you; but enough) ſaith, or tells you; <hi>Do good to them that do evil to you, love your enemies; pray for a pity ſave, deliver, help relieve, ſuccour, comfort,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>thoſe who hate and envie you, who blaſpheme or ſpeak evil of you; thoſe who ſin againſt you, who perſecute, and would deſtroy you.</hi> And this, in truth, is Goſpel, Good-ſpell, or true and right telling and ſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or ſpelling indeed and in truth; when it's thus put together, that is, when the ſpeaking and doing, the heart and the hand, are joyned herein: Chriſt did good to ſinners, loved ſinners, and gave his life for ſinners, even thoſe who perſecuted and blaſphemed him.</p>
            <p>The Goſpel is properly and truely a Reconciliation, reconciling, or Reconciler rather, of things that differ, are at oddes or enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; it's the doing away of all enmities, the caſting down or taking away all partition-walls: the higher the enmity, the greater the oddes; the vaſter the difference, the greater, the higher, the more glorious, excellent, and beautiful, is the Reconciliation or Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciler. It is indeed that ſpirit of life and power, of light and love, which really, truely, and in very deed, reconciles all things unto or takes all things into it ſelf; it ſelf being reconciled unto all things: and, in truth, that or he which is not fully, wholly and perfectly, in every jot and tittle, in him or it ſelf, reconciled to another, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly perfectly reconcile, or preach the Goſpel of Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation perfectly, to that other: It's not a bare preaching or ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but it's real reconciling, or uniting of thoſe things which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118022:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>either really do differ, or at leaſt ſeem ſo to do; and that in the heighths, lengths, bredths, and depths of oddes, enmity, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, or contrarieties; how elſe could the heighths, lengths, bredths, and depths of the Reconciliation or Reconciler appear? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
5.18,19,20. <hi>And all things are of God, who hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled us to himſelf by Jeſus Chriſt, and hath given to us the miniſtery of reconciliation, to wit, that God was in Chriſt, reconciling the world unto himſelf, not imputing their treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes unto them, and hath committed unto us the word of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation. Now then we are ambaſſadours for Chriſt, as though God did be ſeech you by us. We pray you in Chriſts ſtead, be ye reconciled to God.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
2.11,12,13,14,15,16,17. <hi>At that time ye wore
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, being aliens from the commonwealth of Iſrael, and ſtrangers from the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants of promiſe, having no hope, and without God in the world. But now in Chriſt Ieſus, ye who ſometimes were afar off, are made nigh by the blood of Chriſt. For he is our peace, who hath made both one, and hath broken down the middle wall of partition between us: having aboliſhed in his fleſh the enmity, even the law of commandments contained in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, for to make in himſelf, of twain, one new man, ſo making peace. And that he might reconcile both unto God in one body by the croſs, having ſlain the enimity thereby. And came and precabed unto them which were afar off and to them that were nigh.</hi> In
<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.8. <hi>This is the grace given to me</hi> (ſaith
<hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>that I ſhould preach the unſearchable riches of Chriſt</hi> (that's the grace given him, he having it firſt preached unto him, <hi>that all might ſee the fellowſhip of the MYSTERY which was HID IN GOD.</hi> In the tenth verſe there you have Gods end or Intent; which is, that his <hi>MANIFOLD wiſdom might be known:</hi> and ſo prays, in verſ.
16. <hi>that God would grant them according to the riches of his glory, to be ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with all might by his ſpirit in the inner man, that Chriſt might dwell in their hearts, that ſo being rooted and grounded
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> love, they might comprehend with all ſaints, what is the heighth; length, bredth, and depth, and to know the love of God that paſſeth knowledge, that they might be filled with all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118022:12"/>the fulneſs of God,</hi> (and verily, leſs will not do it:) for ſo long, ſo far or ſo much as I apprehend any man or thing to be an enemy unto me, ſo long, ſo far, and ſo much muſt I of neceſſity be an enemy unto him or it: there it's ſaid, <hi>God was in Chriſt, reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the world unto himſelf:</hi> how was that? by preaching ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and declaring himſelf fully, wholly, perfectly, every jot and tittle, reconciled unto it. The Goſpel indeed is that Loadſtone which draweth all things unto or rather, and indeed and in truth, that great
<hi>Elixir,</hi> or Philoſophers ſtone, which turneth all things it touches into its own nature; but it muſt touch them firſt.</p>
            <p>I could ſay much more; but I bear with you forbear and ſpare you: I have no evil will unto any of you; I am enemy to none; neither would I hurt any, becauſe no man nor no thing, can hurt me; but, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>All things ſhall work together for my good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude; were Chriſt, or his Meſſengers his Apoſtles, ſo fearful, ſo timerons, (it's written of them, that they <hi>preached openly</hi> and <hi>boldly,</hi> and <hi>waxed more and more bold</hi> by their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings) although the powers were wholly and altogether engaged againſt them as theſe men are? who, if they have not the powers chiefly and wholly engaged for them, yet are they very little, if at all, engaged againſt them.</p>
            <p>I would offer it to conſideration, whether the primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans would not have thought and judged it ſufficient enough; if the Magiſtrate had not engaged againſt them, although he had not in the leaſt declared or engaged for them? And would not any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, any ſober, any quiet peaceable-minded man or men now, judge him or themſelves to have due and true juſtice and equity done them by the Commonwealth, to have every way, and in all things, equally the ſame priviledges and reſpects with others, from and by the Commonwealth; which is all that is pleaded for, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, in reference to every one, as to himſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Who is The Commonwealths, under the beſt and ſureſt bonds of love unfained, in all faithfulneſs to be commanded,
<hi>Robert Norwood.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:118022:12"/>
            <head>Omitted in the Printing, <hi>Pag.</hi> 21.</head>
            <p>Col. 1.16. <hi>For by him were all things created that are in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and that are in earth, viſible, and inviſible, whether they be thrones, or dominions, or principalities, or powers: all things were created by him and for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As there you ſee all things were made by him. ſo in
<hi>verſ.</hi> 20. you ſhall finde all things to be again reconciled or ſaved by him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By whom</hi> (that is, by Chriſt) <hi>it pleaſed the Father to reconcile all things to himſelf, by him whether they be things in earth, or things in heaven: even you that were ſometimes alienated, and enemies in your minde by wicked works, hath he now reconciled.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
